Finding Aid for R. M. Wenley Papers 1879-1931
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
R. M. Wenley Papers
1879-1931
Wenley, R. M. (Robert Mark), 1861-1929.
Professor of philosophy at Glasgow University and University of Michigan. Extensive correspondence, scrapbooks, lecture notes, addresses, newspaper clippings and other papers relating to questions of philosophy and to his activities at University of Michigan; diaries, 1896-1927, relating to his European travels and career at the University; and photographs.
86359 Aa 2; Ac
11 linear feet
1 oversize folders
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The collection was the gift of Mrs. T. Luther Purdom, Mrs. Herbert C. Sadler, and Mrs. C. D. Campbell (donor nos. 129 and 4645 ) and came to the library in 1937 and 1968.
The collection is open for research.
Robert Mark Wenley was born July 19, 1861 in Edinburgh, Scotland. He enrolled at the University of Glasgow where he won honors in philosophy and came under the influence of Scottish Hegelian philosopher Edward Caird. Among his other teachers were Lord Kelvin in physics and John Nichol in English literature. Because of his health, Wenley interrupted to studies traveling in France, Germany, and Italy. He returned and received his master of arts degree in 1884 and his doctor of philosophy in 1895. In addition, he received a doctor of science degree from the University of Edinburgh in 1891. From 1886 to 1894, he was assistant professor of logic at the University of Glasgow serving. For most of this period, 1888 to 1895, Wenley headed the philosophy department at Queen Margaret College in Glasgow. In 1896, he was invited to come to the University of Michigan to succeed John Dewey at head of the department of philosophy department.
Although influenced by the Hegelianism of John and Edward Caird, Wenley considered himself an objective idealist. At the University of Michigan, he was a popular and influential teacher, knowledgeable in both science and classical scholarship. In addition, Wenley was a prolific writer, authoring hundreds of magazine articles and reviews. He also authored important monographs, including Socrates and Christ (1889); Aspects of Pessimism (1894); and The Life and Work of George Sylvester Morris (1917).
Wenley was a Fellow of the Royal Society of Edinburgh, the Royal Society of Literature, a members of the Aristotelian Society, the American Psychology Society, and a member of the council of the Goethe Society of London. From 1925 to 1927, he was a director of the American University Union in Europe. He died in March 29, 1929.
The Wenley papers have been divided into the following series: Correspondence; University of Glasgow/Queen Margaret College; Biographical and personal; Notes from University of Michigan and other courses and lectures; Speeches and addresses; Miscellaneous; and Scrapbooks.
Subjects:
Europe--Description and travel.; Philosophy.; Voyages and travels.; University of Glasgow.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Philosophy.; University of Michigan--Faculty.Faculty.; Wenley, A. G. (Archibald Gibson), 1898-1962; Wenley, R. M. (Robert Mark), 1861-1929.
Subjects - Visual Material:
Ann Arbor (Mich.)--Dwellings.; Club (Ann Arbor, Mich.); Dwellings--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Living rooms.; Quadrangle Club (University of Michigan); Wenley, R. M. (Robert Mark), 1861-1929.; Wenley family.
Contributors:
Adams, George Plimpton, 1882-1961.; Angell, James Burrill, 1829-1916.; Angell, James Rowland, 1869-1949.; Baldwin, James Mark, 1861-1934.; Barbour, Levi L. (Levi Lewis), 1840-1925.; Beal, Junius E. (Junius Emery), 1860-1942.; Bishop, William Warner, 1871-1955.; Britton, Frederic H.; Butler, Nicholas Murray, 1862-1947.; Caird, Edward, 1835-1908.; Carhart, Henry S. (Henry Smith), 1844-1920.; Chang, Wyszie Shionyu.; Clements, William L. (William Lawrence), 1861-1934.; Cooley, Charles Horton, 1864-1929.; Cooley, Mortimer E. (Mortimer Elwyn), 1855-1944.; Dewey, John, 1859-1952.; Donaldson, James, Sir, 1831-1915.; Duff, Robert A.; Flint, Robert, 1838-1910.; Fraser, Alexander Campbell, 1819-1914.; Frost, Robert, 1874-1963.; Fuller, George N. (George Newman), 1873-1957.; Gallagher, Michael James, 1866-1937.; Goldman, Emma, 1869-1940.; Hobbs, William Herbert, 1864-1952.; Hutchins, Harry B. (Harry Burns), 1847-1930.; Kelsey, Francis W. (Francis Willey), b. 1858.; Ladd, George Trumbull, 1842-1921.; Lloyd, Alfred H. (Alfred Henry), 1864-1927.; Masson, David.; Mencken, H. L. (Henry Louis), 1880-1956.; Murray, John Clark, 1836-1917.; Osborn, Chase S. (Chase Salmon), b. 1860.; Romanes, George John, 1848-1894.; Russell, Bertrand, 1872-1970.; Sinclair, Upton, 1878-1968.; Ten Hoor, Marten, 1890-; Vibbert, Charles Bruce, 1877-1950.; Woodward, Robert Simpson, 1849-1924.
Genre/Form:
Diaries.; Photographs.; Scrapbooks.
- Correspondence
  - Undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - 1879-1884 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - 1885 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - 1886 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - 1887 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - 1891 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - 1892-1893 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - 1894 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - January-June 1895 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - July-December 1895 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - 1896 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - 1897 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - 1898-1900 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - 1901-1905 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - 1906 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - 1907-1908 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - 1909 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - 1910 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - 1911 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - 1912-1913 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - 1914 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - 1915-1916 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - 1917 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - 1918 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - 1919 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - 1920 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - 1921 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - 1922-1923 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - 1924 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - 1925 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - 1926 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - 1927 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - 1928 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - 1929-1931 (Box 1, Folder 34)
- University of Glasgow/Queen Margaret College
  - University of Glasgow course notes and lectures
    - RMW notes as student, 1880-1884; 9 volumes (Box 11)
    - RMW lectures and notes as teacher, 3 volumes; 1 folders (Box 11)
  - Queen Margaret College
    - RMW lectures and notes as teacher, 6 volumes; 1 folders (Box 11)
  - Edinburgh Summer School, 1895-1896 (Box 11)
  - Miscellaneous university and Scottish materials
    - Re. Edward Caird (Box 2, Folder 35)
    - Printed programs of Scottish affairs and events (Box 2, Folder 36)
    - Programs from the University of Glasgow (Box 2, Folder 37)
    - Lists of students at the University of Glasgow and their grade reports (Box 2, Folder 38)
    - Examinations and student papers from the University of Glasgow (Box 2, Folder 39)
    - Papers concerning Wenley's activities at the University of Glasgow (Box 2, Folder 40)
    - Handbills and miscellaneous printed material from the University of Glasgow (Box 2, Folder 41)
    - Political poems (Box 2, Folder 42)
    - Wenley's records and grade reports at the University of Glasgow (Box 2, Folder 44)
    - Printed testimonials favoring Wenley's appointment to academic positions in Scotland, 2 folders (Box 2, Folder 45-46)
- Biographical and personal
  - Obituaries of Robert Mark Wenley, 1929 (Box 2, Folder 47)
  - "Looking Backward: A Veteran's Review" (Box 2, Folder 48)
  - Autobiographical material (Box 2, Folder 49)
  - "Recollections, reflections and impressions of a vagrant Scot: an essay in informal autobiography", 1916; 3 folders (Box 2, Folder 50-52)
  - University of Glasgow honorary degree, 1901 (Box 2, Folder 53)
  - Diplomas and citations (Folder AC)
- Notes from University of Michigan and other courses and lectures
  - "Philosophy of Religion", 5 folders (Box 2, Folder 60-64)
  - "Early Greek philosophy", 3 folders (Box 2, Folder 65-67)
  - "Literature in the Victorian Era", 3 folders (Box 2)
  - Shakespeare, 3 folders (Box 2, Folder 71-73)
  - Protagorean Principle (Box 3, Folder 74)
  - Science and skepticism (Box 3, Folder 75)
  - Cause, skepticism, system, etc., 2 folders (Box 3, Folder 76-77)
  - Evolution (Box 3, Folder 78)
  - Stoicism (Box 3, Folder 79)
  - "Some Stoic Dogmas" (Box 3, Folder 80)
  - Bibliography of philosophy (Box 3, Folder 81)
  - Re "synthesis of knowledge, skepticism, egotism, etc." (Box 3, Folder 82)
  - Sophists, Protagoras, etc. (Box 3, Folder 83)
  - Epistemology, logic and psychology (Box 3, Folder 84)
  - Hegel, etc. (Box 3, Folder 85)
  - "The history of Philosophy and the dialectic of the logic of Hegel" (Box 3, Folder 86)
  - Plato and philosophy since Hegel (Box 3, Folder 87)
  - Hegelianism, psychology, socialism, etc. (Box 3, Folder 88)
  - Browning, Thackeray, the Historical Novel, and Tennyson (Box 3, Folder 89)
  - John Ruskin, the contributions of Scotland and of women to modern literature, and Shakespeare (Box 3, Folder 90)
  - "Art and Morality", Shakespeare plays, literature criticism, etc. (Box 3, Folder 91)
  - "A comparison of the poetical characters of Aeschylus and Sophocles" (Box 3, Folder 92)
  - English Poetry course (Box 3, Folder 93)
  - State interference and lectures in Britain (Box 3, Folder 94)
  - Ethics course (Box 3, Folder 100)
  - Philosophy course in Schelling, Hegel, and Kant (Box 3, Folder 101)
  - Bible class and "The Western World Wonder-Child", 1908 (Box 3, Folder 102)
  - Metaphysics (Box 3, Folder 103)
  - "The Idealistic Movement" (Box 3, Folder 104)
  - "Kant to Hegel" (Box 3, Folder 105)
  - Hegel, 1896-1897 (Box 3, Folder 106)
  - Stoicism (Box 3, Folder 107)
  - "Philosophical Introduction", 1910 (Box 3, Folder 108)
  - Novelists of the nineteenth century, 1896-1897 (Box 3, Folder 109)
  - Evolution and religion, circa 1885 (Box 3, Folder 110)
  - Smollett, 1919 (Box 3, Folder 111)
  - Henry Adams (Box 3, Folder 112)
  - Politics, 2 folders (Box 3, Folder 113-114)
  - Introductory class, September 1896 (Box 3)
    (also used in succeeding years)
  - Course I: Philosophy Introduction, 1905-1907 (Box 3)
  - History of Modern Philosophy (Box 3)
- Speeches and addresses
  - Miscellaneous speeches and papers, 21 folders (Box 4, Folder 114-135)
  - Papers and addresses regarding education, 10 folders (Box 4, Folder 136-145)
  - Notes and addresses concerning literature, 3 folders (Box 4, Folder 146-148)
  - Notes and addresses, 4 folders (Box 4, Folder 151-154)
  - Philosophy papers and addresses, 4 folders (Box 4, Folder 155-158)
  - Addresses concerning religious issues, 4 folders (Box 4, Folder 159-162)
- Miscellaneous
  - University of Michigan examination questions (Box 5, Folder 170)
  - University of Michigan administrative responsibilities, etc. (Box 5, Folder 171)
  - Miscellaneous, 2 folders (Box 5, Folder 172-172)
  - Essays (published and unpublished) and miscellaneous notes, 8 folders (Box 5)
  - Papers; include manuscript of Wenley's Socrates and Christ (Box 5)
  - "Judaism and Philosophy of Religion" galley proofs (Box 5)
  - Book reviews (Box 5)
  - Miscellaneous notes and papers (Box 5)
  - Programs of non-university affairs, 2 folders (Box 5)
  - Photographs, 3 folders (Box 5)
    (See also photos in Ac oversize folder)
  - Diaries, 1896-1927; 3 volumes (Box 6)
    (some years not included)
  - American University Union, London, notebooks, 1925-1927; 8 volumes (Box 6)
  - Miscellaneous notebooks, class registers, etc., 13 volumes (Box 6)
  - Non-Wenley notebooks (Kate Gibson?), 5 volumes (Box 6)
- Scrapbooks
  - 1889-1919 (Box 7)
  - 1884-1914 (Box 7)
  - 1914-1915 (Box 7)
  - December 1915-March 1918 (Box 8)
  - March 1918-December 1919 (Box 8)
  - December 1919-September 1923 (Box 9)
  - October 1923-1925 (Box 9)
  - April-November 1889 (Box 10)
  - 1902-1910 (Box 10)
  - August 1925-April 1926 (Box 10)
  - December 1926-July 1927 (Box 10)
  - Scrapbook (miscellaneous) (Box 10)
  - Foldered clippings, 7 folders (Box 10)
Selected Index to Correspondents
Adams, George Plimpton, 1882-1961.
Nov. 11, 1927
Angell, James Burrill, 1829-1916.
1895-1896, Feb. 28, 1998, June 10, 1901, June 2, 1906?, Jan. 31, 1907, Nov. 11, 1908, Jan. 15, 1909, Nov. 12, 1914
Angell, James Rowland, 1869-1949.
Dec. 6, 1897, Oct. 25, 1916, Aug. 9, 1927
Baldwin, James Mark, 1861-1934.
Dec. 11, 1897
Barbour, Levi L. (Levi Lewis), 1840-1925.
Dec. 10, 1897, Dec. 11, 1897, Jan. 6, 1908, Sept. 7, 1917
Beal, Junius E. (Junius Emery), 1860-1942.
Jan. 8, 1906, Nov. 14, 1917, Sept. 1, 1923, Mar. 2, 1926
Bishop, William Warner, 1871-1955.
Sept. 5, 1917
Britton, Frederic H
July 29, 1908, Aug. 3, 1908
Butler, Nicholas Murray, 1862-1947.
Dec. 8, 1897, Apr. 19, 1902, Nov. 13, 1917
Caird, Edward, 1835-1908
May 8, 1891, Apr. 21, 1894, Jan. 28, 1896
Carhart, Henry S. (Henry Smith), 1844-1920.
Mar. 16, 1909
Chang, Wyszie Shionyu
Aug. 18, 1924, Apr. 28, 1928
Clements, William L. (William Lawrence), 1861-1934.
July 2, 1915
Cooley, Charles Horton, 1864-1929.
Dec. 27, 1924
Cooley, Mortimer E. (Mortimer Elwyn), 1855-1944.
Aug. 23, 1921
Dewey, John, 1859-1952.
Dec. 6, 1897, Jan. 8, 1918
Donaldson, James, Sir, 1831-1915.
Mar. 3.1895, Mar. 20, 1895
Duff, Robert A.
Mar. 13, 1893
Flint, Robert, 1838-1910.
Apr. 16, 1894, Apr. 1, 1895, Aug. 4, 1900, Aug. 30, 1900, Aug. 31, 1900, Mar. 31, 1902
Fraser, Alexander Campbell, 1819-1914.
Mar. 6, 1894, Jan. 26, 1895, Apr. 3, 1895
Frost, Robert Lee, 1874-1963.
Dec. 12, 1924
Fuller, George N. (George Newman), 1873-1957.
Mar. 1, 1918
Gallagher, Michael James, 1866-1937.
Oct. 31, 1924
Goldman, Emma 1869-1940.
Oct. 11, 1912
Hobbs, William Herbert, 1864-1952.
Apr. 25, 1916
Hutchins, Harry B. (Harry Burns), 1847-1930.
Dec. 13, 1897, Feb. 19, 1926, Aug. 9, 1927
Kelsey, Francis Willey, b. 1858.
Dec. 9, 1897, Apr. 2, 1910, Dec. 25, 1914, Oct. 3, 1917, Oct. 4, 1917, Oct. 5, 1923, Dec. 29, 1924
Ladd, George Trumbull, 1842-1921.
Dec. 8, 1897
Lloyd, Alfred H. (Alfred Henry), 1864-1927.
May 31, 1896, Dec. 6, 1897, Oct. 1, 1918
Masson, David.
Aug. 10, 1891
Mencken, H. L. (Henry Louis), 1880-1956.
July 27, 1921?, Aug. 12, 1921?, Aug. 17, 1921?
Murray, John Clark, 1836-1917.
Dec. 7, 1897
Osborn, Chase S. (Chase Salmon), 1860-1949.
Dec. 20, 1918, July 31, 1919, June 14, 1922, July 20, 1922
Romanes, George John, 1848-1894.
Apr. 31, 1891, July 16, 1891, 1896?
Russell, Bertrand, 1872-1970.
Apr. 28, 1914, May 7, 1914
Sinclair, Upton, 1878-1968.
Aug. 30, 1922
Ten Hoor, Marten, 1890-
May 13, 1928, Feb. 17, 1929, Feb. 25, 1929
Vibbert, Charles Bruce, 1877-1950.
Sept. 13, 1917, Sept. 22, 1917, Oct. 28, 1918, Mar. 7, 1919, Sept. 6, 1919, Sept. 9, 1919
Woodward, Robert Simpson, 1849-1924.
Dec. 21, 1917